原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/XxDZYuAZxSc
原视频发布日期：20201001
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
It's been a couple of months
这已经几个月过去了
since I took a long hard look at what SpaceX are up to with the Starship project.
从那时起我就在认真研究SpaceX在Starship项目上正在做的事情
Since the SN5 flight we've seen SN6 do the same thing.
自从SN5飞行之后 我们就看到SN6也在做同样的事情
And I'll be honest I had half expected SpaceX to skip this entirely given that it's using an older alloy
而且说实话 我曾差点以为SpaceX会完全跳过SN6 因为它使用的是旧版的合金
and seeing how fast serial number eight was progressing.
而且注意到SN8的进度是如此之快
But it took off from the launch pad accompanied by a burst of flame from the fuel supply disconnect.
但在SN6从发射台起飞时 伴随着燃料供应断开的一阵火焰
It started going sideways and controlling itself using basically the gimbal from the engine.
它开始侧向机动 基本上是用发动机的矢量推进来控制自己的运动的
This time the footage showed that there was no fire on the exterior of the engine itself
这次的视频显示 发动机结构表面没有喷火
so they addressed the problem that we saw with SN5
所以他们解决了我们在SN5上看到的问题
and uh yeah then it would descend towards the landing site
接着 SN5就向着陆点下降
It deployed the landing legs and it carefully touched down on to complete the test
它部署了着陆腿 小心翼翼地碰到地上并完成了测试
so that was 150 meter hop.
这就是150米的跳跃
And you know since then I've also seen some photos of the landing legs
在那之后 我也看到了一些着陆腿的照片
and I think I figured out how the shock absorbers on the legs are designed.
我想我知道着陆腿上的减震器是怎么设计的了
So they're like box girders with holes are drilled in
所以它们就像箱形梁一样 上面钻了很多孔
and if you look the closer to the bottom of the leg the larger the holes get.
而如果你注意看 越靠近腿的底部 孔洞就越大
So this in turn makes the legs weakest at the bottom.
所以这就使得腿部的底部最薄弱
So as it lands hard it compresses and it compresses harder and harder and harder.
所以当它着陆得比较重的时候 就会被压缩 而且压缩得越来越厉害
But absorbs the shock as those legs crush.
但是在着陆腿压碎的同时 震动也就被吸收了
So yeah they're basically improvised crush cores. Absorb the landing shock.
那么是的 这些基本算是临时制作出来的粉碎芯来吸收着陆时的震动
And you don't transmit it to the rest of the structure.
这样震动就不会传到结构的其他部分
Elsewhere by the way SpaceX also released a video showing another successful fairing catch from a Falcon 9.
顺便说一下 SpaceX还发布了一段视频 展示了另一次成功的猎鹰9号整流罩捕获
While SpaceX have been reusing fairings for Starlink launches
虽然SpaceX一直在Starlink任务中使用用过的整流罩
it looks like most of the fairings aren't being caught in the net.
但是看起来大部分的整流罩都没落到网上
But they're instead you know soft landing in the water and you're getting fished out.
而是软着陆溅落到水中并被捞出来
So it's nice to see an actual catch.
那么看到一次真正的捕获是很好的
Back in Boca Chica the SN7.1 test tank was tested.
回到博卡奇卡 SN7.1储罐进行了测试
It was supposed to demonstrate new alloys and welding techniques that were used for the later versions.
SN7.1应该是用来验证新的合金和焊接技术 用于以后的版本
And it reached new levels of pressure popping at eight bars or eight atmospheres of pressure
它的耐压程度达到了新的水平 直到在8巴或8个大气压的压力下爆炸
or nine at the bottom because of the head with the liquid in the tank.
而底部达到了9巴 这是因为储罐的头部里装有液体压力更大导致的
Also on the test stand right now is serial number eight and it has wings.
现在试验台上还放着带有翼面的SN8
But anyway for me the most important thing in the last month
但无论如何 对我来说 上个月最重要的事情则是
is the appearance of the first vacuum version of the Raptor engine or RapVac as I like to call it.
第一款真空版猛禽发动机的出现 或者我喜欢叫它RapVac(真空猛禽)
We've seen dozens of Raptor engines reach various levels of testing
我们已经看到了几十台猛禽发动机达到了不同的测试水平
but these are all the sea level versions.
但这些都是海平面版本
The new RapVac is equipped with a much larger nozzle
新的真空猛禽配备了一个更大的喷管
but otherwise it seems broadly similar to the previous example engines we've seen.
但除此之外 它似乎与我们之前看到的试制发动机大致相似
It even has the two axis bearing at the top to support gimbaling.
甚至在顶部 有两轴轴承来支持矢量摆动
Even although the RapVacs are supposed to be fixed in the structure.
即使真空猛禽应该是固定在结构中的
So generally speaking what's important here for a vacuum engine
所以一般来说 对于真空发动机来说 重要的是
is the expansion ratio between the throat of the combustion chamber and the exit at the nozzle.
燃烧室喉部和喷管出口之间的比 也就是膨胀比
The higher this ratio
该比率越大
the more performance the engine can extract from the exhaust gases as they expand through it.
意味着 当废气通过喷管膨胀时 发动机可以从废气中提取更多的性能
According to Elon the expansion ratio for the RapVac prototype is 107
据马一龙介绍 真空猛禽原型机的膨胀比为107
compared to the regular Raptor which we think is about 40.
相比之下 我们认为的普通猛禽的膨胀比在40左右
However having large nozzles isn't for everyone.
然而大喷管并不是万金油
Right. When the exhaust gases expand through the nozzle the pressure of the gas drops.
没错 虽然说废气通过喷管膨胀时 气体的压力就会下降
And if the pressure of the exhaust gases drop too far below atmospheric pressure
但如果废气的压力降得太低 低于大气压的话
then the atmosphere can start to push back inside the nozzle
接着 大气就会开始挤进喷管内部
and this causes a phenomena called flow separation right.
而这就会造成边界层分离
The exhaust gases get pushed away from the nozzle wall
废气会被推离喷管壁
and you know that can cause trouble with the engine.
而这会给发动机带来问题
There's a video here showing the Space Shuttle main engines throttling up towards full power
这段视频 显示了航天飞机主发动机正提升至满功率
and before they reach full power you can see this flow separation around the edges of the nozzle.
在达到满功率之前 你可以在喷管的边缘 看到这种边界层分离
And then as it throttles up it gets pushed down.
而随着功率的提升 空气就被退离了喷管壁
During this if you look carefully you can also see the nozzles are wobbling
在这期间 如果你仔细观察 你还可以看到喷管在晃动
because this phenomena generates significant like transverse forces
因为这种现象会产生显著的横向力
which if they are kept up they can damage the engine
如果这样持续下去 就会损坏发动机
so at sea level engines don't have large nozzles so that they don't encounter this phenomena.
那么海平面发动机的喷管并不大 也就不会遇到这种现象
So anyway according to Elon the RapVac is very much a prototype engine
那么按照马一龙的说法 (这台)真空猛禽仍是一个原型机
and it's not optimized for the final performance.
而且并没有为最终版性能进行优化
I think they've actually optimized this for development time.
而我觉得他们实际上是朝着缩短研发时间的方向进行了优化
Firstly they've chosen a nozzle size which is right at the limit of what they could test in the atmosphere
首先 他们选择的喷管尺寸正好是他们能在大气层中测试的极限尺寸
without having big problems with flow separation.
而不会出现边界层分离的大问题
If you watch the test video of the actual Raptor
如果你实际看了那台真空猛禽的测试视频
you can see a little bit of flow separation around the edges
你可以看到边缘有一点边界层分离的现象
but the the test was clearly successful.
但测试显然是成功的
The nozzle looks to be fully regeneratively cooled
喷管看起来是完全再生冷却的
and this is distinct from the Merlin vacuum engine
这与真空梅林发动机不同
which includes a very large radiatively cooled nozzle extension.
而真空梅林发动机采用了一个非常大的辐射冷却喷管延伸段
However you can't really do this on Starship
然而 在Starship上不能这么做
because on the Merlin that is essentially exposed to the surface of space
因为在梅林发动机的情况中 (发动机的喷管)是直接暴露在太空中的
but in Starship the vacuum versions are up inside the skirt
而在Starship的情况中 真空版发动机被放在裙板内
which means that if they get hot, they would radiate heat into the interior of the skirt
这就意味着 如果变热 就会将热量辐射到裙板内部
so instead they have to keep that nozzle cool during firing without baking everything else around it.
所以必须在发射过程中保持喷管的冷却 而不至于把周围的东西都烤焦
So they of course do regenerative cooling, the pump propellant methane through the walls.
那么他们当然会使用再生冷却 泵出甲烷推进剂流过喷管壁
So with the older engines
那么在老式的发动机上
the way that you would manufacture a regeneratively cooled nozzle would be
制造再生冷却喷管的方式会是
by arranging thousands of individual pipes into the desired shape
把成千上万根管子排列成所需的形状
and then you would braise weld those together
再把这些管子焊在一起
and this is kind of a laborious process.
而这是一种费劲儿的过程
The Raptor nozzles are made in a different way.
而猛禽的喷管是以不同的方式制造的
What they do is I believe they start with a sheet of copper
我觉得他们是先从铜板开始
and then they machine out channels into it.
然后用机器加工出通道
Then they sandwich this between two sheets of inconel and that is your channel wall.
然后再把铜板夹在铬镍铁合金中间来得到喷管壁
Presumably this same technique is also being used for the larger vacuum nozzle on the Raptor engine
据推测 这种技术也被用于真空猛禽的更大的喷管上面
but either way there's also some extra reinforcing being added to the Raptor Vacuum.
但无论如何 真空猛禽也有一些额外的强化措施
it's possible that they weren't sure how much flow separation would work and they needed extra strength.
有可能是他们不确定边界层分离的效应如何 而需要提供额外的强度
It's also possible
也有可能是
these stiffeners are just being used for development while it's being used inside the atmosphere.
这些加固件只是开发时在大气中使用
Also the interior looks white and nobody's really sure what this is.
另外没人知道白色的内部到底是什么
But I think most people think that it's a sort of white ceramic
但我觉得大多数人会认为这是某种白色的陶瓷
that's designed to reflect heat and possibly protect the chamber wall from oxidation.
用来反射热量 同时也可能保护燃烧室壁不被氧化
So when the engine is firing, you can see that has a very pronounced mach diamond just beyond the nozzle.
那么在发动机点火时 你会看到喷管外有一个很明显的马赫环
This is very similar to the one that we see in the Space Shuttle.
这与我们在航天飞机上看到的非常相似
You can also see that as soon as the exhaust gases exit the nozzle
你还可以看到 当废气从喷管中排出时
they get compressed down by the atmospheric pressure
它们就被大气压给压下去了
and of course as they get squeezed down that's where you get that hot spot.
而在废气在向后排出并挤压的过程中 当然就形成了热点
It actually surprises some people to know that despite all the energy and violence
除了这样的能量和力量 仍有一件事让人们震惊
the exhaust gases that are leaving that nozzle at supersonic speeds.
那就是废气以超音速的速度离开了喷管
They're also leaving that at lower pressure than the atmosphere around us.
而它们离开时的压力也比我们周围的大气要低
There's also some telltale bright beads along the interior of the nozzle
在喷管内部也有一些明显的亮光珠子
and you know that's where the flow separation is happening.
你知道 那就是发生边界层分离的地方
So anyway clearly they can't put a larger nozzle on this test one
那么很明显 他们不能在这个测试版发动机上再安装更大的喷管
because it would then have problems at sea level.
否则就会在海平面运行时产生问题
They would have to have a special testing facility.
他们必须有一个特殊的测试设施
There are testing facilities that let you test vacuum engines but they're big and expensive.
有一些测试设施可以让你测试真空发动机 但它们很大而且很昂贵
So the video also lets us hear the Raptor startup sequence and it is really fast.
那么这段视频也让我们听到了猛禽的启动过程 速度非常快
You can hear those turbo pumps spin up in a fraction of a second.
你可以听到那些涡轮泵在几分之一秒的时间里旋转起来
There's a small burst of flame (or a) burst of cold cryogenic gases
有一小段火焰(或)低温气体的爆发
and then finally the full ignition in all its glory.
最后则是辉煌的完全点火
Compare this to the Space Shuttle's engine startup sequence
对比一下航天飞机的发动机启动时序
that takes several seconds to ramp up.
也就是需要几秒钟的时间来提高(涡轮泵的)速度
The Shuttle engines they start using only pressure from the tanks.
航天飞机的发动机只用储罐的压力来启动
And you know they take a little longer to get up to speed.
所以他们需要更长的时间来达到所需速度
But the Raptor is a more complicated engine.
但猛禽是一个更复杂的发动机
iIt has this full flow cycle
它使用全流量循环
where it has two turbo pumps which are both dependent on each other pumping fuel.
它有两个涡轮泵 这俩都依赖于对方来泵送燃料
And if one pump runs faster than the other, it messes up with the fuel oxidizer ratio for both turbines.
如果一个泵比另一个泵运行得更快 就会破坏两个涡轮的燃料氧化剂比
So it's safer to get the turbines up to speed very quickly using a separate high pressure gas supply.
所以比较安全的方式是 使用单独的高压气源 让涡轮泵快速启动
So that rapid startup is used by all the Raptor engines.
那么这种快速启动的方式被所有的猛禽发动机所采用
It's not just a vacuum version.
不仅仅是真空版本
And actually of course it's a very good thing.
当然实际上这也是一件非常好的事情
If you are falling from the sky and depend on starting up your rocket engines quickly to land
如果你从天上掉下来 依靠快速启动火箭发动机来降落的话
then you want the rocket engines to start up very quickly.
那么你会希望火箭发动机能够很快地启动
Anyway this engine is very likely going to be improved.
总之这个发动机很有可能会被改进
Elon has stated publicly that he wants to aim for a performance of 380 seconds of specific impulse.
马一龙曾公开表示 他希望追求380秒比冲的性能
But based on 300 bar chamber pressure and the known expansion ratio
但根据300巴的燃烧室压力和已知的膨胀比来看
this puts the performance in the ballpark of about 370 seconds.
这台发动机的性能大致在370秒的程度
If they want to raise it that extra and get up to 380, they'd need a larger nozzle
如果他们想把比冲提高到380秒 就需要更大的喷管
and there might be some room in the rear end of the Starship.
而Starship的尾部可能还有一些空间
But I don't think there's really enough to get to where they need to be.
但我不认为真的有足够的空间让他们到达比冲目标
But instead of expanding the nozzle, they could actually shrink the throat down instead.
但与其扩大喷管 不如把喉部缩小
And that would let them reach the expansion ratio between the throat and the nozzle.
这样就能达到喉部和喷管之间的膨胀率
Rough math suggests that if they got the expansion ratio to about 200 to 1
粗略的计算表明 如果他们把膨胀率提高到200比1的话
while maintaining the 300 bar chamber pressure that would satisfy the 380 target.
同时保持300巴的燃烧室压力 就可以满足380的目标
Doing this would require a lot more changes to the engine.
要做到这一点 就需要对发动机进行更多的改动
The power head would probably have to be redesigned a bit.
动力舱可能要重新设计一下
The smaller throat means that for the same pressure you've got lower propellant flow rates
更小的喉部意味着在相同的压力下 推进剂流速会更低
which would probably mean changes to both of the pumps to optimize them for the different flow rates.
这可能意味着要同时改变两个泵 以优化它们以适应不同的流速
And of course such a design would then have an exit pressure so low
当然 这样的设计会使出口压力降低到这种程度
that it couldn't be tested with the full nozzle at sea level
使得全尺寸喷管不能在海平面上进行测试
so again more testing resources needed there.
所以也需要更多的测试资源
But that's for the future.
但那是将来的事
Right now it's great to see this working.
而现在 看到这台发动机能正常工作是很好的
And I am eager to see how this evolves over time.
而且我很想看到这台发动机在未来的发展
And yes in the next few days we are expecting to see some testing on the very first winged Starship build.
是的 在接下来的几天里 我们有望看到第一艘造好的有翼Starship的一些测试
SN8 is on the launch site with the rear flaps attached.
SN8已经附上了后部翼面 放在发射场上
What we'll probably see is the usual setup of a pressure test, cryogenic test, static fire.
我们可能会看到压力测试 低温测试以及静态点火的常规安排
But unlike the previous tests I expect
但与之前的测试不同的是 我期望
if they're all successful then we might see them take it back and fit a nose cone
如果这些测试都成功 那么我们可能会看到他们把它收回来 并安装一个鼻锥
rather than going with a mass simulator seen in the previous test
而不是使用之前测试中看到的质量模拟器
or we might see a mass simulator first.
或者我们可能会先看到一个质量模拟器
They could fit the mass simulator on the test site.
他们可以在试验场上安装质量模拟器
They might not be able to do that with the nose cone without returning it to the high bays.
但鼻锥的安装就必须要返回到大厂房里进行了
Either way they're probably aiming for another 150 meter hop with a mass sim or a nose cone.
无论如何 他们的目标可能是用质量模拟器或鼻锥再跳150米
But then yes the ultimate plan for this is a flight to 15 kilometers
但没错 之后就是最终的计划 进行15公里高度的飞行
followed by shutting down the engines
然后关闭发动机
and letting it fall under aerodynamic control in the belly flop maneuver.
并让它进行腹部翻转的动作 在空气动力学的控制中下降
And finally as it gets low, it'll adjust its aerodynamics, fire up its engines
最后当它到达低空时 它会调整空气动力学外形 并启动发动机
and hopefully perform a safe landing.
并希望能进行安全着陆
But honestly this test is the one I'm really worried about for now
但老实说 我目前真正担心的就是这个测试
because they've demonstrated everything else.
因为他们已经验证了所有其他的东西
They've never even demonstrated this with a sub scale model.
(但是)他们甚至从来没有用小尺寸模型来验证过(15公里跳这个过程)
This is something that's entirely in computer simulation
这完全是计算机模拟的结果
so this is a bold move to be trying to do a full-scale flight of this.
所以这样一个全尺寸的飞行尝试是一个大胆的举动
But hey you know they are getting ahead of themselves now
但你知道 他们现在的进度很快
in terms of building prototypes faster than they're blowing them up.
主要是建造原型机的速度比炸毁原型机的速度还快
So they can probably afford to do a full-size test
所以他们可能有能力做一个全尺寸的测试
assuming the test doesn't result in the thing going out of control
假设测试的结果不至于使飞船发生失控
and you know smashing into their test site.
并砸到他们的发射场
That would probably set them back.
而这则会拖住他们的进度
Either way,
无论哪种方式
yeah we're getting towards being able to see a proper test flight of SN8 towards the end of the year.
是的 到今年年底 我们会看到SN8的试飞
I also won't be surprised if when Elon does his Starship update presentation
我觉得在马一龙进行Starship更新演讲的时候
that they have a full SN8 with a nose cone and flaps and wings all installed
SN8就能完全建造好了 并装上了鼻锥和所有翼面
but we'll see what happens there.
但我们还得走着瞧
Until then,
在那之前
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]